Civil War Letters and Miscellanea Collection MS 060
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Letters and correspondence, 57822
  - Charles Garlick (formerly MS 007), 38280
    - Letter Aug 30, 1863, Portsmouth, VA, 38286 (Box 2, Item 8)
      We had a very pleasant journey coming down here. We left Fort Hood Bedlowes Island the 19th took the boat there from South Amboy there took the cars for Philadelphia which were so crowed that we with several other took the platform on the outside and I lay down and slept all of the way Philadelphia arrived there about daylight took a good breakfast at the Cooper shop refreshment saloon went from there over to the Baltimore depot took the cars there about 8 o'clock arrived at Baltimore at 3 o'clock pm stayed there until 6 o'clock took supper and stayed until next day about 10 o'clock took the cars for camp distribution stayed there till I got tired of that place (We left there the 27th came to Washington stayed over night marched over to Georgetown took the boat about 9 o'clock for Fortress Monroe arrived there at 1 am the next day stayed there about an hour and then took the boat across to Portsmouth where we are now. I must close for we have come to fall in and go up to the Gen. Harland head quarters. Give my respects to all that enquire and write soon and tell me all of the news. We have pretty good news here this morning from Charles so good bye for this time.
      As ever your affectionate son
      PS. Direct to Charles D. Garlick
      Co I 8th Regiment
      Portsmouth Virginia
      Via, Washington D. C.
    - Letter 1863? Portsmouth, VA, undated; 38285 (Box 2, Item 9)
      I did not have a chance to express the sashel?? myself but left it with a chum of mine Henry Warnock he said he should express it and take a receipt. I should not pay the express for I did not have money enough and shall not get any for this time for I did not get here in time for muster so I shall have to wait two months more. In the sachel was one black dress coat and brown sack coat and pair of blue pants two or three white shirts one pair of boots I have forgotten what else I shall write to Henry Warnock tomorrow if I have time and will find out about the sachel. When you write to Alice tell her that I hope she will excuse me for not writing to her for I hardly get time to write home but tell her I am innocent of the charge she against me of having someone of more consequence to write to but if she is bound to court martial me I shall have to stand it but I shall not plead guilty. It seams to me that they might have had some of those weddings that have come off and are to come off before I left New Haven so I might have got a chance to see if not taste some of the cake I must close for this time as it is roll call and I am pretty sleepy. Give my respects to all that enquire and tell Uncle Seymore that I am glad he has got home I would like to see him and the rest of the folks Please excuse the bad writing ? In haste your
      Affectionate son (pls write soon)
      Co I 8th Regt C. V.
      Portsmough, Va
      Via Fortress Monroe
      Co I 8 Regt.
    - Letter Jun 15, 1864 Fortress Monroe, VA, 38284 (Box 2, Item 10)
      Chesapeake Genl Hospital
      Fortress Monroe Va
      June 15th 1864
      I received you kind letter of the 13th just today and was very glad to hear from you and glad to learn you are all well. I am feeling better now than I have in some time before. I think the salt water breeze had a pretty good effect on me. It is a very pleasant place here this summer quite cool to what it is a little inland. There is a large government farm here that furnishes us with all the fresh vegetables that is needed in the hospt. We have had given peas about three weeks which don't go against the constitution very bad. I guess not. I have given up all thoughts of getting north this summer. I am detailed here now in the dining room to wait on the table I have to work about 5 or 6 (?) hours each day and get pretty good grub which is the main thing with a soldier you know and am pretty well contented to pass three months here when my time will be out. I saw Ashbels name in the paper yesterday as being wounded also, two others from my Co. I heard there was but 15 men left of the Regt but I do not believe any such thing. I mailed a picture yesterday for you of Hampton Hospital and a few days since I have mailed a book and I will mail another with this. I have got the letter which you send me to New Haven. It came just in time for I was broke and out of tobacco and stamps and had to do my own washing. I will close this for I have got to write a letter to Billy Stilson (?) yet tonight. Give my respects to all that enquire and write soon.
      From your affectionate son
    - Letter Jul 23, 1864 Fortress Monroe, VA, 38283 (Box 2, Item 11)
      Near Fortress Monroe Va.
      July 23rd 1864
      I now take my pen in hand to acknowledge the receipt of your kind and welcome letter of the 19th (which came to hand to day) it found me well as usual and I hope this will find you on the mend. I am doing pretty well here now. I am detailed in the Officers Mess room where I do not have to work very hard and get my good which you know is of the most consequence to a soldier as long as he can get his he is right. I commence at 5 in the morning and work till about 9 in again 1/2 past 7 in the evening.
      Thank kind fortune I am on the last two months of three years service and in a fair way for a discharge an honorable one too I hope. The weather here is awful hot one day and cold the next. We have had a little rain for the last week before that it was awful dry. I don't want you to send me any money for I can get along better without it you can for two months and as for those shts if George wants them fix them for him and let him wear them and save what money he can for I want to take him to New Haven with me when I come home I want him to see a little of city life the folks. As for your doing better by going to the bridge I do not know about that I think with the right management you can do better there you are sure of enough to live on any way if and will not have to buy it. I know wages and groceries of dry goods are high but produce is a high in proportion so as far as I can see it is all long as it is broad and I think you have got the best end of the bargain after all. I wrote a letter to Alice the other day and have got an answer and I must answer that to night so I hope you will excuse this from your
      Affectionate son
      P. S. The folks Alice wrote are all well and send their love to you they want me to come out there this fall. I will see about that by and by.
      C. D. Garlick
      Fortress Monroe Va.
      P.S. Please write soon as it was two weeks since I wrote to you before I got an answer and I begun to feel anxious about you at home.
      Yours truly
      Charles
      P. S. Again I want to know if Father has ever seen anything of Bill Stilson in New Milford lately I have written to him but get no answer if you see him tell him I will give him if he don't write to me.
    - Letter Aug 6, 1864, Near Fortress Monroe, VA, 38282 (Box 2, Item 12)
      Chesapeake Genl. Hospital
      Near Fortress Monroe Va
      Aug 6th 1864
      My Dear Parents
      I now take my pen in hand to answer your kind letter of the 31st ? which came to hand to day and found me as well as usual and I hope this will find all well and getting along good. I am glad to hear that father is on the gain tell him he should look out for the old cow next time and not let her out flank him. It is awful hot and dry here now. We had a little shower tonight but it did not amount to much. It only made the mosquitoes thicker than ever and most blood thirsty. I tell you they will almost carry a fellow off four of them will get a stretcher and come to our tents and try to get us on for to have a ride but we can't see it they want to get us on and then fly off with us and are just as likely to drop us in Richmond as any other place. Well I guess this will do for once. Lieut. Chas. Irwin came down here last Thursday. He is sick with a fever. He says the boys are all in fine spirits. Capt. Roberts is in the Corps Hospital sick. He has not been well this summer but has kept with the Regt. till a few days since when he was sent to this hospital. Well what do you think about the war. Things are progressing favorably and they Genl Grant has a given them a little bit of a kick and in my opinion we can look for more one of these days that will set Mr. Johnny secesh a flying. I am detailed as night watch now. I am on duty from 9 o'clock at night until one then have the remaining part of the hours to myself. Please excuse this for the paper is worse then poor and the pen is worse yet. From your affec son
      Chas D. Garlick
  - Single Letters, 57823
    - Samuel Mather Mansfield, Jan 26, 1864; 57824 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Samuel Mather Mansfield from Middletown, CT or the 24th CT Vol. Infantry which saw action at Port Hudson and the Red River Campaign. Testimonial letter in support of F.E. Camp late lieutenant of the 24th CT. January 26, 1864.
    - Benjamin Wright, Aug 10, 1864; 57825 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Camp 10th Conn.Vols. Before Petersburg Va.Sept.llth 1864 My Dear Abbie are For a wonder we left quietly in camp to day. some thing must be wrong although Genl.Terry ordered the fatigue party back to camp last Sabbath.but I did not think Col.Plaisted could leave us in camp.he would have had us to work some where on our Brigade line,it is possible however he may have received orders forbidding it to day.their was a detail made last night for to day.but for some cause it was countermanded this morning.Although Sunday the men have been very busy cleaning up. Washing their clothes,and fixing their tents.it is the only chance they have,and they have to improve it.if it is Sabbath,to morrow they will without doubt be on fatigue all day and at night go in the trenches.when I got in camp last night I found my tent fix up pretty well. my Pioneer and Sam had been to work.I found a good bunk and a good table.things quite convenient. I felt a little inclined to leave my tent last night,and go down in my Co. street under the breastwork.! thought the Bullets were flying over rather uncomfortably thick.Some of them pretty close.I could hear them whistle by.I remained in my tent,woke up this morning and found every thing safe. during the unguarded watches of the night,I had been guarded by an eye that never sleeps.and kept from all harm. As yet I have heard nothing about any service to be held to day.I suppose however the Chaplain will hold one service some time during the day.although his and Camps time is very much occupied at this about getting Camp Mustered as Major.that appears to engross his whole time for a few days past all at once last week,he left us at the front and went into camp.as yet fie they have not succeeded very well,hor do I think they will.if they do I don't wish to remain longer in the Regiment if it were possible to get out. the Chaplain was just around says he intends having service at 2 Oclock he had invited the 24th Glee Club to lead the singing. as though we could not lead our own singing.I think it would have looked better if he had invited them to unite with us as it is our meeting.evry one to their notion however as the old woman said when she kissed the cow .quere notion of hers however. It ' has been very quiet thus far to day but few shots been fired along the line.appears to be a genl.regard for the Sabbath I wish we might always have it.I tremble when I think of the effect on the Thousands in our Army of this disregard of the Sabbath on their after life,after the close of the War and they have returned to their homes.I fear to a great extent we shall be come a Nation of Sabbath breakers.God grant deliverance from this great Sin. 8 PM We recieved the mail a short time ago I recieved three letters.one very short one from you,one from Cousin Louisa,and one from Lieut.Linsley.he was at home in Northford is doing very well.expects to return to the Regiment about the 25th.I shall hail his arrival with joy.the Chaplain had service this afternoon.we had none to night.I have been down in my Co. street part of the evening singing with some of the boys.I quite like my Co. have some pretty good boys.I have written Adelia quite a long letter to day.I hope she will answer.the next letter I have to answer is Marys I may commence it to night,if not I will do it to morrow,unless I am on some detail. God bless you and Bennie is my earnest prayer. loving ever Benjamin
    - Edward Lockwood Letter, June 24, 1863; 57826 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Originally part of the Truman Warner Papers, MS 026. Lockwood, Edward-Civil War Letters (copies) | 1862-1865 Box: 26 Folder: 89-90. Perhaps of the 1st Regiment, New York Light Artillery. Letter complains about freeing the slaves, fighting to end slavery, Hooker's command, and men remaining at home.
    - William B. Green, 1864; 57831 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      William B. Green was from New Hampshire and served with the 2nd US Sharpshooters. Green writes to his mother about digging and the 4th of July.
    - John L. Allen, September 27, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      5th Connecticut Volunteer Infantry; XX Corps; letter written to brother from Atlanta-discusses confederate raids and nature of the land.
    - Miss Mollie Schell, Galletin, TN - Poetical Scrap Book, 1864; 57830 (Box 3, Item 1)
      Inscribed: "This book contains clippings from newspaper findings during the Civil War collected by Mrs. Shearer then Miss Schell and arranged by her during he eight months imprisonment in on room by order of Brig Gen Paine 1862-1863 because she would not take the oath allegiance which she could not conscienciously do."
      Gallatin, TN was under the control of the controversial, General Eleazor A. Paine, commander of the Union railroad guard from November 1862, to April, 1864. According to some accounts he abused his power.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Originally part of the Truman Warner Papers, MS 026. Provenance unknown. Box 51.
- Cartes De Visites, 57827
  - Paste-ins from Souvenir of the Centennial Exhibition, 1860-1870; 57828 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    3 unidentified persons which had been pasted into the a book commemorating CT's Centennial Exhibition. The book is inscribed to a New York family Cassazza. (The book is part of the CTRoom collections T825.F3.C8 1877)
  - Miscellaneous CDVs, 1861-1865; 57832 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Alfred Dickerson, Lt. 16th CT
    Ezra Mathewson, Lt. 18th CT
    Samuel L. Williams, Lt. 8th CT
    Henry W. Hibbard, Pvt. 18th CT
    Albert O. Comstock, Cpl. 14th CT V.I.
    Edward W. Bliss, Lt. 11th CT V.I (could also be Francis Bliss of the 17th CT V.I.)
    Each soldier has some information regarding their unit and service.
  - Photo album from the Alfred Geddes Collection, 57829 (Box 1, Item *)
    Originally part of the Alfred Geddes Collection (MS 008). 40 images and the original portfolio.